hey what's up guys my name is Jonah
welcome back to my C++ series so today
we're gonna be talking all about type
punning in C++ and type planning is
really just a fancy term for just us
kind of getting around the type system
in C++ so C++ is a strongly typed
language which means that we have a type
system we don't declare everything as
auto I mean we kind of can because of
that kit word but in other languages
like JavaScript there are no kind of
sense of variable types really and we
just have we don't need to declare a
variable type when we create a variable
and when we accept it in its parameters
into functions or anything like that we
don't have a type system really but it's
a plus plus of course we do have a type
system we have to declare things as
integers or doubles or bullying's or
structs or classes all that stuff when
we actually create variables however
this type system is not really enforced
as strongly as it is in other languages
such as Java where it's really hard to
get around types and even c-sharp but
you can do it but it's a bit more work
in C++ whilst types are kind of enforced
by the compiler you can directly access
memory which means that you can kind of
say that hang on a minute I know that at
the moment in my code I've been using
this type as say an integer but actually
I'm gonna just grab that memory that
same memory and just treat it as a
double now or as a class or something
like that
and you can just get around the type
system really easily now whether what
you should is going to again depend on
your actual circumstance in some cases
you absolutely should not circumvent the
type system because the type system is
there for a reason
and you probably don't want to be
playing around with a 2-month unless you
have a good reason but in other cases
it's totally okay to do that for example
let's just say we had a class and we
wanted to write it out as a stream of
bytes well instead of kind of going
through everything as assuming it's like
a structure of primitive types it
doesn't have pointers to other places in
memory we can just kind of reinterpret
that entire struct or class or whatever
we have as just a byte array and just
write that out or stream it somewhere
right we don't have to even care about
what types are in it so we know the size
we can just get the
get to get the data access it and then
just put it somewhere so in a lot of
cases it is really useful and it means
that it's kind of that raw I guess
low level access that is why I really
like C++ and why suppose was is so
effective in applications where
performance is required anyway not
talking let's just dive in take a look
at a few examples this is something that
I use quite often so you'll probably see
it in other videos and especially like
in the OpenGL serious and the game end
deserts and all that so you'll see
plenty of this this is just gonna be a
basic overview but let's just dive in
and see what we can do okay so in that
first example I kind of declared an
integer well I just said that I had an
integer and then I just wanted to treat
it as a double well of course in this
case that's probably gonna result in and
pretty weird-looking double and not
something that you want to do but again
just to demonstrate how this works I'll
show you anyway we're going to make it
double we're gonna call it value and
we're gonna set it equal to a that's
kind of step one now first of all you
can see it works right everything seems
to work fine if we were to print this
out like this and I even put a
breakpoint over here get at five you can
see what we get is 50 okay interesting
reasonable I guess I mean it converted
our integer to a double now so it's 50
let's take a look at the memory so I'll
go debug Windows memory and memory 1 I'm
gonna go to the memory address of a and
take a look at what is in there ok cool
32 zero zero zero zero zero zero okay
makes sense 32 is 50 in hexadecimal now
let's take a look at the memory address
of value now first of all is going to
have a different memory address the
second of all well we know how many
bytes it is it's eight bytes look at
that
it's completely different I mean 49 49
and 40 over here and like what's going
on it's it's not even it's not it's not
the same memory at all because what's
actually done is this just actually done
a conversion it's converted an int into
a double because that's what happens if
you do something like this now in this
case it was an implicit conversion
meaning we didn't actually tell it to
convert anything if we wanted to be
explicit we could write double a like
that which is fine I mean it doesn't get
anything in this case we don't have to
write double here because it will do an
implicit
but if we wanted to be explicit this is
actually what's happening is converting
that a from being an integer into an
actual double now what if we wanted to
just take that existing memory we saw 32
and then zero zero zero zero zero zero
in our memory I wouldn't take that same
memory but I just want that memory to be
treated as a double how do I do that
well the first thing to do that that we
need to do there are a few ways actually
but this is the kind of wrong way I
guess we take the memory dose of a and
then we cast that to a double pointer so
and a double by double pointer I mean
obviously a double pointer not two
pointers now this part here is of course
just taking the memory address of a so
this gives us an integer pointer and
then we're converting that into pointer
into a double pointer and then we
obviously need to get back to having a
double so how do we go from pointer to
the actual type we dereference it and
that's what we get so this is this looks
a bit weird maybe if it's the first time
you've seen it but essentially what
we're doing here is we're type punting
our integer into a double so if we hit
f5 now let's see what we get okay so
it's a pretty weird-looking double
I mean it's negative nine point two
eight plus sixty-one so yeah whatever
clearly not something that we'd probably
want to do but again it's just an
example if we take a look at the memory
address of a you can see that of course
it has 32 like that and if we take it
the memory address of B oh sorry I'll
value you can see what we have over here
now what you also see is if you remember
that we have eight bytes of double the
rest is our initialize memory because
what we've done here is something pretty
bad because these are different sizes
right I mean we've taken a four byte
integer and kind of decided to a double
so what that's done since we've
converted an int pointer into a double
pointer and then dereferenced it that's
actually gone ahead and looked four
bytes past our integer and grabbed that
memory which is not our memory it's not
the memory we have for integer so this
is very bad and it could even cause a
crash in some circumstance it's
definitely something you want
do I mean we've copied that memory into
a new double value blog so that's safe
so we haven't written and we if we can't
at this point even if we do write to
value we're not going to be writing to
memory this on ours but we definitely
have read from memory that's not ours
that's not good let's take a look at a
more practical example so what I'm going
to do now of course if you didn't want
to just just a quick note if you didn't
want to actually create a whole new
variable and you just wanted to access
this int as if it was a double then you
can just add an ampersand to the end of
this double here which will just
reference it and not copy it into a
whole new variable and that way you will
be actually editing this integer memory
so that is dangerous because if I decide
to write something like 0 into here then
guess what it's actually going to write
8 bytes instead of 4 but we only have
space before this might even crash so
let's take a look at a more practical
example what if I have a struct called
entity and this has two variables in X Y
now we know really say I hope you know
that if we have let's just initializes
to 5 and 8 if we have something like
this in memory then really all that
struct is is like it it is it is made up
of those two integers it has literally
those two integers and that's it if we
look at its memory you can see we have 5
& 8 that's it the struct itself does not
contain any kind of padding any kind of
data whatever if it's an am C struct
then there has to be at least one bites
the will be something in there because
we need to be able to address that
memory and we can't address it it's not
there so we have to have at least one
byte instructive and if it is empty but
if we have variables in there like in x
and y that struct is just two integers
that's all it is there's no like extra
data that says this is an entity struct
it's not how any of that works it's just
the two integers so what we can do here
is we can actually just treat this empty
struct as an int array or maybe just
extract one of its integers by not even
doing it so you don't why it's take a
look so I could just say a dot X and
that would give me my X variable but
what I could do also is just say well
let's make it a read out of it so this
will be a raw array say in point up
call this out of my position equals the
memory address of a and then just cost
that Twitter points up like that and now
if I wanted to print this out I'll just
write it as CDC out position zero and
then comma position one like that as if
it was Justin all right and you can see
there I have it
five eight I mean I'm accessing it like
it was an array because I've converted
it into an array basically I've said
that this entity memory address contains
the beginning of an int array right or
it just contains a pointer to an integer
and then I've just looked one integer
ahead using the same kind of method what
I could do is something even crazier
perhaps let's just say I wanted to get
that Y variable out of it now of course
any sane person would just write that
and fact that's probably what I would
write as a well I mean man because I'm
pretty sane but what you could do is you
could get the memory address off e like
that converted into maybe like a char
pointer again not sure why you would but
let's just say that you did that is of
course of one byte in size so we need to
go four bytes forward like that and then
convert that memory into an int pointer
and then dereference that and then we
have access to Y so let's go ahead and
print this crazy piece of card like that
and I'll check that out we get a which
is of course the Y position of the
entity but the point is what we've done
here is we're just kind of just reverted
to raw memory operation so I mean that
simples Clause does really well which is
why it's such a powerful language one of
the big reasons why it is such a
powerful language because it has that
kind of it can manipulate memory really
easily and really freely and memory is
by far one of the biggest things we
actually have to deal with when we're
actually programming so whilst this code
probably should never exist like in real
applications because it's crazy and of
course in this case you can just use a
dot Y it can be very useful if you don't
want to deal with kind of copying or
conversions because again if we wanted
this as an array
well we can't like if you let's just say
you wanted to create you know how did I
get positions or whatever as an int
array well how would you do that well I
mean I guess like well you would have to
kind of do it well this is not an array
so I have to just create like a new int
array right now because this isn't a
function and you know we're not taking
in like some kind of memory to put that
that array into we probably need to
create our own array which means we need
to heap allocated and then copy that and
I don't even want to write this code
it's disgusting it's terribly slow it's
awful what I could do instead is just
return well I don't know memory address
of X right now this of course really
depends on the user not trying to do
something like position two because
there is no third element and that's
going to go away bus to memory however
you can see that now what I have access
to if I fall you get positions he is an
actual int array with two elements in it
that I can access and I haven't I can
also write to it so I can say position
zero equals two and I've changed the
x-coordinate of my entity but also I you
know I haven't copy anything I haven't
copied memory redundantly I've just
linking to the same memory I'm just
choosing a different way to actually
interpret that memory if you don't want
to deal with the raw cost so you can use
reinterpret class to do exactly the same
thing we will have a video for simple
space costs in the future reason I
haven't done one yet it's because I
don't use them too often - you see style
passed most of the time I probably
should use if I spot star class but what
are you gonna do anyway that is
basically tie pudding it's just us being
able to say I'm gonna treat this memory
I have as a different type than it
actually is and you can see if we can do
that really freely all we really need to
do is just get that type as a pointer
and then cost it to a different pointer
and then we can dereference it if we
need to and just deal with it anyway I
hope you guys enjoy this video if you
did please hit the like button let me
know what you think about try planning
and this type system and why like why
try planning is useful and why you love
it so much or you do I hated I don't
know
well how do you feel about it leave your
thoughts in the comment section below if
you want to support the series please go
to Petra non compos - to Cherno huge
shout out as always to all my lovely
supporters this series would not be here
without you guys so thank you and I'll
see you next time goodbye
[Music]